<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A conspiracre [sic] of the twelve bishops in the Tower, against Mr. Calamie, Mr. Burton, Mr. Martiall, and many other worthy divines, &amp;c. As also how they obseurely [sic] made those articles, wherein Mr. Pym and the other Parliament men were impeached. Shewing likewise their treacherie, how they would have escaped out ot the Tower. With a description of the true cause that the City of London and Westminster are day and night in armes. And of that notable abuse, which was done last Thursday night, when the city was called up to rise in arms in the night, both in Cheapside, Covent-Garden, and St. Georges field in Southwark.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80376</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E181_32</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R958</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873576</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873576</idno>
            <idno type="VID">126053</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80376)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 126053)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 32:E181[32])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A conspiracre [sic] of the twelve bishops in the Tower, against Mr. Calamie, Mr. Burton, Mr. Martiall, and many other worthy divines, &amp;c. As also how they obseurely [sic] made those articles, wherein Mr. Pym and the other Parliament men were impeached. Shewing likewise their treacherie, how they would have escaped out ot the Tower. With a description of the true cause that the City of London and Westminster are day and night in armes. And of that notable abuse, which was done last Thursday night, when the city was called up to rise in arms in the night, both in Cheapside, Covent-Garden, and St. Georges field in Southwark.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Bond,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: illustration filmed with following item.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Calamy, Edmund, 1600-1666 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Burton, William, 1575-1645 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Marshall, Stephen, 1594?-1655 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Pym, John, 1584-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Temporal power --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:126053:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CONSPIRACIE OF THE TWELVE BISHOPS IN THE TOWER, AGAINST <hi>Mr. Calamie, Mr. Burton, Mr. Martiall, and many other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Divines, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s alſo how they obſcurely made thoſe Articles, wherein Mr. Pym and the other Parliament men were impeached.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hewing likewiſe their treacherie, how they would have eſcaped out of the Tower. With a Deſcription of the true Cauſe that the City of London and Weſtminſter are day and night in Armes.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of that notable Abuſe, which was done laſt <hi>Thurſday night,</hi> when the City was called up to riſe in Arms in the night, both in Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, Covent-Garden, and St. Georges field in Southwark.</p>
            <p>London. Printed for W. Bond, 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:126053:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:126053:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <figDesc>central circle flanked by the English lion on the left and the Scottish unicorn on the right and containing the initials of King Charles, all of these figures enclosed within a rectangle flanked by angel on the left and right</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>THE CONSPIRACY OF THE TWELVE BISHOPS IN THE TOWER: <hi>Againſt Mr. Calamie, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Burton, Mr. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, and many other worthy Divines, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE tyrannicall uſurpation of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and their Eccleſiaſticall inſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hath beene generally acknowledged to be the prime cauſe of theſe Diſcords, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous diſtractions among the people at this time. They have been kindling the fire of diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a long time in this kingdome, and now
<pb facs="tcp:126053:3"/> they have almoſt brought the ſpark of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious minds to a full flame. But I hope God will ſtill divert their wicked intents, and as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore all their uſurping tyrannie, and nefarious machinations <hi>in famum evanuerunt,</hi> have come to nothing, ſo ſtill their conſpiracies ſhall be confounded. They have alwayes envied the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie of good and painfull Miniſters of the Goſpell, and as they ſaw them flouriſh the more in the truth of the holy Scripture, gaining the affections of the people, ſo ſtill the more did they alwayes emulate them. But the Parliament having judiciouſly perceived their intents, did not think them fit members of the Houſe, and therefore have placed them in an other houſe more meet for them, I mean the Tower, which they have moſt deſerved. Where being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, they ſtudied with all diligence, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity to ſubvert either the intents of thoſe, who ſhould oppoſe them, and were the Authors of their impriſonment. Having thus molded their reſolution, they privately made ſeven Articles againſt Mr. <hi>Pym,</hi> and four other worthie Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment men, wherein they were all arraigned of High Treaſon. And when they had obſcurely compoſed, they ſent it to be preſented to the Kings Majeſtie, and that he would vouchſafe to give his Aſſent thereunto, and proclaim them Traitors. Thus we may perceive their malicious minds, who, when they ſaw men glorious in the kingdome, and that ſtood for the ſafety, peace
<pb facs="tcp:126053:3"/> and proſperitie of the Realm, did ſtudie to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant thoſe Noble Members, being the next way to ſupplant the whole Kingdome beſides. Thus we may underſtand their diligence to ſet the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Kingdome together by the ears: thus we may ſee their intents to alienate the Vpper Houſe of Parliament from the Lower houſe, and the King from both; yet being ſomewhat fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of their expectation of impriſonment of thoſe Members, whom they impeached: their malice would not ſtop there, but entended farther. And now being croſt in their former ſtratagem, they proceeded unto a ſecond: wherein they privatly againe, and obſcurely compoſed Articles againſt M. Calamie, M. Burton, M. Martiall, &amp;c. with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other famous Divines, ſtriving to ſuppreſſe the laborious and painfull Miniſters of the <hi>Word and Goſpell;</hi> for becauſe they could not bring the Parliament into diſſenſion and diſcord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, labouring to eject the chiefeſt Members thereof: they ſtrived to reduce the Church to Hereſie, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd promiſcuous diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, intending to ſuſpend the chiefeſt pillars thereof,</p>
            <p>But I hope that their envie and emulation will ſhortly be diſſipated, and although they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect theſe men with themſelves in the tower, yet J beleeve they may ſtay long enough for them.</p>
            <p>If the parliament would bee pleaſed to call theſe
<pb facs="tcp:126053:4"/> Biſhops to their triall, it would be great honour to themſelves, greater ſafety to the Kingdome, and eſpecially greateſt honour to God and the propagation of his holy Goſpell. For they dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concurre together in machinations, either how they may depopulate the Realm, or elſe how they themſelves might obſcurely eſcape from the Tower: Once they had concluded to ſhave themſelves, put on perriwigs, and gray clothes, and ſo they thought to have eſcaped from thence, but their treacherie was diſcovered, and notice given to the Parliament therof. Who did immediately thereupon ſend for ſome of the Guard, and gave ſtricter charge of their fidelity: who very faithfully promiſed the ſame.</p>
            <p>But the City of <hi>London</hi> being in ſuch extreame pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill, and danger, did induce many to ſtand in their own defence; for they knew not what Treachery, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and other popiſh Recuſants might conſpire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Trained <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nds doe both day and night wai<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in London and Weſtminſter to defend themſelves from the wicked Conſpiracies of their tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous enemies. But one great abuſe done unto the City I cannot omit; when as laſt Thurſday night ſome Company had bin drinking very late in the night, and were reſolved to do ſome exploit, that ſhould be heard of in the City: and one of them immediatly replyed, that they would cry about the ſtreets, that the Papiſts were ariſing, and every man ſhould preſently ſtand on his owne ſafeguard. It was concluded on, and crying thus in the City, and calling for every man to come in his owne defence for feare hee ſhould bee burnt in his
<pb facs="tcp:126053:4"/> bed, for the Papiſts were riſen. There was immediatly many thouſand Citizens came incontinently with their Muskers charged all with bullets, ſome with Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts, others with pikes, ſome with ſwords and the like weapons, Common-garden was immediatly filled with ſouldiers, in Cheap-ſide there were many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands ſtood in their Guard, and in St. Georges Field in Southwarke there was an infinite number of men in Armes. But if theſe roguiſh diſturbers of the city could be apprehended, I doubt not but that they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive condigne puniſhment according to their deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
